Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs 1896-2008 (bulk 1896-1937)
ML31.J64
Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959
Johnson, Eric
circa 105 items 2 containers 1 linear foot
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of photographic prints taken by Swiss-born American composer Ernest Bloch during the first half of the 20th century. These prints were developed during the 1970s by photographer Eric Johnson. The collection also includes a variety of research materials related to Bloch and his experiences with photography.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Barjansky, Alexandre--Photographs.; Barjansky, Catherine--Photographs.; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959.; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959.; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959. Eric Johnson collection of Ernest Bloch photographs. 1896-2008.; Clement, Ada--Photographs.; Hodgehead, Lillian--Photographs.; Johnson, Eric.; Menuhin, Yehudi, 1916-1999--Photographs.; Sessions, Roger, 1896-1985--Photographs.; Ysaÿe, Eugène, 1858-1931--Photographs.
Subjects
Photography.; Portrait photography.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Photographic prints.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, Eric Johnson, 2009.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Other Repositories
Over 6000 negatives and 2000 prints are housed in the Ernest Bloch Archive at the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds the
Ernest Bloch Collection
.
Access and Restrictions
The Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Well known to most as a composer, Ernest Bloch is also recognized for his considerable genius in the field of photography. Bloch took up the camera in his teenage years and constantly documented his experiences using still images until his death in 1959. Throughout his life, he produced over 6000 negatives and 2000 prints that are now housed in the Ernest Bloch Archive at the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona.
Bloch’s subject matter ranged from landscapes to self-portraits, family portraits, and other images of nature and people that surrounded him. His photographs were praised by such contemporary authorities as Alfred Stieglitz and captured the interest of other prominent photographers, including Ansel Adams, Georgia O’Keeffe, Edward Weston, and Diego Rivera.
The prints in this collection were selected for development as a product of photographer Eric Johnson's exploratory study of relationships between music and photography conducted in the early 1970s. The resulting publication, A Composer’s Vision: Photographs by Ernest Bloch (1972) documents his findings.
Scope and Content Note
The Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs contains 105 black and white prints, the majority of which date from 1896-1937. Notable prints include "mushroom lady" (1912), trees depicting the characters of various composers, including Bach, Beethoven, and Debussy (1931 and 1935), and images of Alexandre Barjansky, Catherine Barjansky, Ada Clement, Lillian Hodgehead, Yehudi Menuhin, Roger Sessions, and Eugène Ysaÿe. Photographs are arranged by date of inscription. "Research materials" contains preliminary and final drafts of Johnson's article, as well as a pamphlet on Bloch published by the Ernest Bloch Legacy Project in 2008.
Arrangement of the Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs
The Eric Johnson Collection of Ernest Bloch Photographs is organized in 2 series:
Photographs, 1896-1976
Research Materials, 1971-2008
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561021
Container List
- Photographs, 1896-1976 (Box 1-2)
  - 1896-1900, 11 photographs (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1901-1910, 10 photographs; Images include: Eugène Ysaÿe, Leon Goetschel, "peasant near Geneva" (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1911-1915, 1917-1920, 14 photographs; Images include: Leon Goetschel, "mushroom lady" (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1916, 18 photographs; Images include: Alexandre Barjansky, Catherine Barjansky, "Schelomo sculpture" (Box-folder 1/4)
  - 1921-1923, 14 photographs (Box-folder 1/5)
  - 1924-1930, 9 photographs; Images include: New Mexico, "Indian", Ada Clement, Lillian Hodgehead (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 1931-1935, 12 photographs; Images include: "peasant", "tree pictures" (Bach, Beethoven, Debussy), Yehudi Menuhin, Alexandre Barjansky, Mary Tibaldi Chiesa (Box-folder 2/2)
  - 1936-1937, 1956-1957, 1976, 10 photographs; Images include: Mary Tibaldi Chiesa (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Undated, 7 photographs; Images include: Roger Sessions (Box-folder 2/4)
- Research Materials, 1971-2008 (Box 2)
  - Articles and publications, Includes: A Composer’s Vision: Photographs by Ernest Bloch (1972) and pamphlet from Ernest Bloch Legacy Project (2008). (Box-folder 2/5)